<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on Rasengangstarr</title><link>https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/projects/</link><description>Recent content in Projects on Rasengangstarr</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 20:12:30 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Vim Wiki Habits</title><link>https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/projects/vim-habits/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 20:12:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/projects/vim-habits/</guid><description>A habit tracker plugin for Vim</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Rasengangstarr/vimwikihabits">Github Page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A few months back, I decided I was going to finally force myself to learn &lt;a href="https://www.vim.org/">Vim&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I ended up building a 60% keyboard with snap in switches (which was a fun project in and of itself), which crucially didn&amp;rsquo;t have any arrow keys, forcing me to learn vim&amp;rsquo;s hjkl control system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/mykeyboard.jpg" alt="My Keyboard">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, somewhere down that rabbit hole, I discovered &lt;a href="https://github.com/vimwiki/vimwiki">Vim Wiki&lt;/a> and Vimscript.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="vim-wiki">Vim Wiki&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Vim Wiki is a vim extension that allows you to create markdown documents that are rendered in vim. Obviously since vim runs in a terminal session that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean much, but it does allow you to do some cool things like bullet point lists, checklists and impressively create hyperlinks between documents.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bundled with Vim Wiki is a diary feature. Using hotkeys, you can create diary entries for the current day, and generate an index page to navigate them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="vimscript">Vimscript&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Vimscript the scripting (duh) language used to create vim plugins. It&amp;rsquo;s quite limited, and you have to jump through some hoops to get anything done, but I spent some time working through &lt;a href="https://learnvimscriptthehardway.stevelosh.com/">This set of tutorials&lt;/a> to get to grips with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="my-project">My Project&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I figured that a cool (and potentially actually useful) extension to the Diary in VimWiki would be a habit tracker.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wanted to be able to define a set of habits, and have them pasted into Diary pages as a list of checkboxes. I then wanted to take those filled in checkbox lists and use them to generate a report of what habits had and hadn&amp;rsquo;t been followed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The code (which you can find on &lt;a href="https://github.com/Rasengangstarr/vimwikihabits">Github&lt;/a>) is an utter mess, but it just about works.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="how-its-used">How its used&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>First, navigate to your vimwiki diary directory, and create a new file called habits.vim. Inside it, enter your habits as a new line seperated list:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/vimwikihabits1.png" alt="screenshot-1635963144">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Save this file, then enter one of your diary entries, (or create one using the vimwiki diary shortcuts:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/vimwikihabits2.png" alt="screenshot-1635963379">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Press &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> :VimWikiHabitsInsert&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/vimwikihabits3.png" alt="screenshot-1635963519">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This should paste your habits as a todo list in the diary entry - check or uncheck them by pressing &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->+&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> over the boxes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then you can simply press &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> :VimWikiHabitsGenerate to view the habit tracker at the bottom of the screen&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/vimwikihabits4.png" alt="screenshot-1635963495">&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="further-work">Further work&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Having gotten the vim plugin bug, I made two further plugins:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Rasengangstarr/vascii">Vascii&lt;/a>, which utilizes the jp2a bash program to render an image file as ascii art directly into a document within vim&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Rasengangstarr/Vimcats">Vimcats&lt;/a>, which takes an image from this &lt;a href="https://cataas.com/cat">Random cat image API&lt;/a> and dumps it into a document within vim&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="conclusions">Conclusions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve not done much with Vimscript since these projects, but I still use Vim every day. I&amp;rsquo;m currently editing this document with the Vim extension for Visual Studio Code, I use a Vim plugin for Visual Studio when I&amp;rsquo;m developing C# on Windows at work, and being able to quickly edit files on my home computer without leaving the terminal is awesome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It takes a while to learn Vim&amp;rsquo;s keys, but once you get the hang of it everything becomes easier, and using the &amp;lsquo;standard&amp;rsquo; way of editing files feels like a huge step backwards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My biggest problem now is accidentally typing :w in the middle of text files when I&amp;rsquo;m using notepad++ at work.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Hugo Static Web Site</title><link>https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/projects/hugo-static-web-site/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 17:30:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/projects/hugo-static-web-site/</guid><description>How I made this site</description><content>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to make some kind of portfolio website / blog for a few years now.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During some downtime at work (caused by a storm taking out the power where our Gitlab instance is stored), I got to googling around new javascript frameworks, looking for something other than the Vue.JS I already used at work to play around with this weekend.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Somewhere down that rabbit hole, I started looking into static website frameworks. Remembering that long time portfolio project idea, I decided to have a play with &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I skim watched &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtIqKaDlqXo&amp;amp;list=PLLAZ4kZ9dFpOnyRlyS-liKL5ReHDcj4G3">This series&lt;/a> on Youtube, then got to work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="installation">Installation&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The official website told me i needed to use &lt;a href="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew&lt;/a> to install Hugo on my Linux machine. I think brew is the Mac-OS package manager, like apt or pacman, but anyway I haven&amp;rsquo;t used it before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The installation process was&amp;hellip; icky:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>/bin/bash -c &amp;quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh)&amp;quot;
test -d ~/.linuxbrew &amp;amp;&amp;amp; eval &amp;quot;$(~/.linuxbrew/bin/brew shellenv)&amp;quot;
test -d /home/linuxbrew/.linuxbrew &amp;amp;&amp;amp; eval &amp;quot;$(/home/linuxbrew/.linuxbrew/bin/brew shellenv)&amp;quot;
test -r ~/.bash_profile &amp;amp;&amp;amp; echo &amp;quot;eval \&amp;quot;\$($(brew --prefix)/bin/brew shellenv)\&amp;quot;&amp;quot; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.bash_profile
echo &amp;quot;eval \&amp;quot;\$($(brew --prefix)/bin/brew shellenv)\&amp;quot;&amp;quot; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.profile
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Didn&amp;rsquo;t read it or check it. I&amp;rsquo;m sure its fine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, once that was done I could run&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>brew install hugo
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>And I was away.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="creating-the-site">Creating the site&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Hugo provides a bunch of commands for configuration etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I created a new directory for Hugo projects:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>mkdir HUGO
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Then jumped in there and created a new site:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>cd HUGO
hugo new site portfolio
cd portfolio
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>And tested it worked by running:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>hugo server -D
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h1 id="adding-a-theme">Adding a theme&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Next I added the &lt;a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/themes/hugo-theme-terminal/">terminal&lt;/a> theme to my site by cloning it&amp;rsquo;s github project into the themes directory of the project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Following the instructions provided by the theme&amp;rsquo;s developer, i ran up the server again with:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>hugo server -t terminal
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>No idea what that -t option does, but it worked.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="messing-with-the-theme">Messing with the theme&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Top level configuration in Hugo is done in the config.toml file at the root directory of the project. Again, the theme developer provided some code to copy paste into there, with a bunch of parameters you can mess with.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, by default the theme renders the accents of the page in orange, so I messed with some different options they provided:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code># [&amp;quot;orange&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;green&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pink&amp;quot;]
themeColor = &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>I also didn&amp;rsquo;t like how everything was smushed to the left on the site, with an ugly bar in the middle, which didn&amp;rsquo;t look anything like the clean examples they&amp;rsquo;d provided:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/uglytheme.png" alt="Ugly offcenter default behaviour">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, looking in that &lt;strong>config.toml&lt;/strong> file I found:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code># set theme to full screen width
fullWidthTheme = false
# center theme with default width
centerTheme = true
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Flipping that &lt;strong>centerTheme&lt;/strong> flag did the trick&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="making-this-page">Making this page&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>To create this page, I used Hugo&amp;rsquo;s command line tool:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>hugo new projects/hugo-static-web-site.md
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>This creates the page in a subdirectory called projects. I also wanted projects to behave as a list page, so scanning the config file, I found and modified this:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>[[languages.en.menu.main]]
identifier = &amp;quot;about&amp;quot;
name = &amp;quot;About&amp;quot;
url = &amp;quot;/about&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>So that &lt;em>Projects&lt;/em> appears in the top bar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, I used this &lt;a href="https://www.nextpertise.net/posts/210424_hugo_markdown_cheatsheet/">Cheatsheet&lt;/a> to make the page.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also wanted to see what it would look like on my phone, so opened a port in the Pop OS (Ubuntu) firewall:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>sudo ufw allow 1313
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>then ran the hugo server command with additional &amp;ndash;bind and &amp;ndash;baseURL parameters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://rasengangstarr.github.io/Portfolio/images/mobilehugo.png" alt="It looks cool on mobile too">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I really like how the menu looks on the mobile version.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="next-steps-and-conclusion">Next steps and conclusion&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Next I&amp;rsquo;ll probably figure out the best way to upload this to github pages and host it there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was shocked at how easy this was to set up. I set everything up and created this page in less than a couple of hours. I&amp;rsquo;ll probably go back and write up some recent projects, sort out the About Page, and write up any future projects on here.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>